NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services Files. 6174/003
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- PTA Meeting w/ Judy Thomas, 1987 (Box 38, Folder 20)
  March 13, 1987. Memo from NYSUT research director Charles Santelli opposing PTA-sponsored Child Abuse bill as impacting rights of teachers, October 16, 1986; text of proposed legislation; related memos re meeting with PTA representatives Judy Thomas and Deborah Zift over bill, January-February 1987
- PTA Legislation Workshop, 1985 (Box 38, Folder 21)
  January 28, 1985. PTA adopted resolutions; correspondence; handwritten notes from legislative workshop
- PTA Project Meeting, 1982-1986 (Box 38, Folder 22)
  National PTA publication, "Looking in on Your School: A Workbook for Improving Public Education," 1982; reprint of New York magazine cover story re upper-tier public schools, January 13, 1986; letter from NYSUT Vice President Antonia Cortese to NYS Congress of Parents and Teachers Vice President Theodore Sturgis expressing willingness to cooperate with PTA on "Looking in on Your School" project under certain conditions, January 10, 1986; agenda for State Advisory Committee meeting, September 24, 1984; revised project timetable
- Pay Equity See also: Medical School Salary Study Merit Pay Salary, 1986-1988 (Box 38, Folder 23)
  "Job Evaluation: A Tool for Pay Equity," National Committee on Pay Equity, November 1987; correspondence from committee; article in Governing, "'Comparable Worth' Revisited: Whatever Happened after Washington State?" June 1988; materials re NYSUT Pay Equity Training; handwritten notes.
- Peer Interaction, 1986 (Box 38, Folder 24)
  Description of types of peer interaction; conceptual discussion paper; description of New York State Mentor Teacher Internship Program (First Year Teacher Assistance Aid); inventory of characteristic teacher interactions at six schools
- Performance – National Commission on Performance-Based Education See also: Effective Teaching Program (Box 38, Folder 25)
  Publications and reports by Educational Testing Service and others for meeting of ETS national commission re evaluating teacher effectiveness; agenda.
- National Commission on Performance-Based Education – Joint Research Project, 1973-1974 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  Report of joint project of NYSUT, SED, and National Commission, "A Study of Teaching Effectiveness in New York State," September 1974; ETS paper, "Policies and Procedures for Control of Confidentiality of Data ," June 1973; ETS report, "A Plan for a Research Program on Teacher Effectiveness," September 14, 1974; ETS confidential minutes of Advisory Board meeting, June 6, 1974; handwritten notes
- National Commission on Performance-Based Education, 1974 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  ETS report, "The Mission of the National Commission on Performance-Based Education: The Commission's Research and Development Strategy; for discussion and approval November 1974"; commission reports: "An Integrated Research Program to Improve Teaching Effectiveness: A Prospectus (Summary)"; " Research Program on the Identification of Teaching Competencies That Affect Pupil Growth (A Summary"; Research and Development Projects of the National Commission on Performance-Based education: Brief Descriptions, October 1974; list of commission members; minutes of Executive Committee meeting, August 20, 1974; agenda for November 7-9 meeting; correspondence
- National Commission on Performance-Based Education – Misc., 1974 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  Related documents and memos
- National Commission on Performance-Based Education, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  Educational Testing Service publication: "A Design for an Accountability System for the New York City School System, June 1972"
- National Commission on Performance-Based Education – Joint Research Project, 1975-1976 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  Educational Testing Service report, "Beginning Teacher Evaluation Study, Phase II, 1973-74: Summary Report"; draft ETS report, "Development of a Plan for Inter-State Cooperation in Research on Teaching Competence from National Commission on Performance-Based Education," June 1975; NYSUT Summary of Research on Teaching and Its Implications for Policy Making: Report on Phase II of the Beginning Teaching Evaluation Study," with supporting material
- Consortium Governance of Teacher Education (Florida Paper), 1974 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  Paper delivered by NYSUT president Thomas Y. Hobart to the National Consortium of CBTE (Competency-Based Teacher Education) Developers, January 1974; scholarly article reprint; clippings
- Performance Assessment – American Education Research Association XV Area Conference (folder 1) See also: American Education Research Association, 1990 (Box 39, Folder 7)
  April, 1990. Papers presented at American Education Research Association Annual meeting re performance assessment of students in Connecticut schools.
- Performance Assessment – American Education Research Association XV Area Conference – ETS (folder 2), 1990 (Box 39, Folder 8)
  April, 1990. Papers re performance assessments tests, by Educational Testing Service
- Performance Assessment – American Education Research Association XV Area Conference – Miscellaneous (folder 3), 1990 (Box 39, Folder 9)
  April, 1990. Papers re restructuring, shared decision making, and testing
- Performance-Based Teacher Education (folder 1), 1972-1976 (Box 39, Folder 10)
  Reports, correspondence
- Performance-Based Teacher Education (folder 2), 1972-1976 (Box 39, Folder 11)
- Teacher Education Hearings: Teacher Preparation and Certifications, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 12)
  Regents Tentative Statewide Plan for the Development of Post-Secondary Education, 1972 (summary of hearings of September 29); background information; chronology; proposed amendment
- Performance-Based Certification, 1970-1971 (Box 39, Folder 13)
  Papers and correspondence; report/mission statement/policy guidelines of the TC-LD Policy Board
- Performance Contracting, 1970-1972 (Box 39, Folder 14)
  Special reports, brochures, testimony, position papers, and fact sheets re contracting to private companies that guarantee a certain level of student performance
- NYS Office of Education Performance Review, 1973-1974 (Box 39, Folder 15)
  Office of Education Performance Review reports: Occupational Education; BOCES; Teacher Absenteeism in NYC; State Education Department's Statewide Evaluation Plan; School Factors Influencing Reading Achievement: A Case Study of Two Inner-City [NYC] Schools; Cost Variations in Driver Education: A Survey of 67 Public School Programs; The Superintendent of Schools: His Role, Background and Salary; An Evaluation of the Role and Background of the Guidance Counselor; statement by NYSUT President Hobart to Office of Education Performance Review re misuse of student testing, October 3, 1974; NYSUT memos analyzing reports; correspondence from office director Daniel Klepak; newspaper clippings
- Personnel, 1986 (Box 39, Folder 16)
  Memo from NYSUT Vice President Antonia Cortese justifying need for one additional clerical staff person in the Division of Research and Educational Services due to growth of Effective Teaching Program, noting need to conduct review for more, November 26, 1986; supporting documentation
- Physical Education (folder 1), 1980-1986 (Box 40, Folder 1)
  Meeting minutes of Ad Hoc Physical Education Subcommittee; correspondence opposing proposal to reduce number of physical education classes, remove certification requirement; materials re mixed competition in interscholastic sports; newspaper clippings
- Physical Education (folder 2), 1981 (Box 40, Folder 2)
  Correspondence and related material re physical education requirement for vocational schools
- Project Redesign, 1971 (Box 40, Folder 3)
  Memo from Lois Wilson to members of NYSTA cabinet re her meeting with assistant commissioner Haake re program in four pilot districts, April 15, 1971; annual reports
- Project Search, 1973 (Box 40, Folder 4)
  Memo to Albert Shanker from Lois Wilson re creation of regional diagnostic and treatment centers across the state, with attached flyer from Plattsburgh Service Center
- Professional Autonomy, 1967-1978 (Box 40, Folder 5)
  Minutes of Professional Autonomy Committee, March 3-4, 1967; press release from NYS Teachers Association announcing hearings on certification, September 4, 1968; memos to Board of Directors re professional autonomy, 1970; press release by State Education Department re testimony by Regent Louise Yavner before Assembly Higher Education Committee re professional discipline, May 4, 1979; professional development proposal by Rhode Island Federation of Teachers, November 9, 1978; newspaper clippings, 1975-76
- Professional Decision Making See: Restructuring/Shared Decision Making
- Professional Development, 1998 (Box 40, Folder 6)
  Discussion item for Board of Regents, "Professional Development Participation, 1996-1997," with cover letter, January 20, 1998; information on licensing/certification for individual school social worker
- Professional Standards, 1971-1984 (Box 40, Folder 7)
  NYSUT conference report re "Teacher Education and Professionalism," May 25, 1977; press releases and letters from various professional associations (engineers, dentists, nurses, CPAs) re proposed Regents Rules Relating to Unprofessional Conduct; State Education Department press release, "Regents Action Gives Consumers More Precise Standards of Professional Conduct," July 28, 1977; statement by Regent Genrich, chair of the Committee on Professional Discipline; text of speech by Jonathan Messerli, dean of the School of Education, Fordham University, "Teacher Militancy and the Public Authority to License and Set Professional Standards," October 13, 1975, with personal note to NYSUT president Tom Hobart; State Education Department paper, "A New Style of Certification," March 15, 1971; NEA directory of teacher standards and practices commissions, 1973; NYSUT memos re state-mandated professional development day, 1984
- Proficiency Exams, 1975-1976 (Box 40, Folder 8)
  Regents External Degrees College Proficiency Examinations, 1975; related brochures; letters to Albert Shanker and Charles Santelli re denials of graduate credit for taking proficiency exam, 1976
- Proposition 13 (California), 1978 (Box 40, Folder 9)
  AFT research report, "The Tax Limitation Movement: The Facts and Issues," September 1978; fact sheet by Citizens Public Expenditure Survey Inc. of New York State (CPES), "Tax Reduction in New York State," re Proposition 13, July 1978; newspaper clippings
- Public Ed. Association, 1982 (Box 40, Folder 10)
  Memos re conference, "Breaking the Cycle of Failure: Schools, Community, and Parents as Working Partners"
- Public Employee Unions, 1975-1978 (Box 40, Folder 11)
  Memo to AFT Executive Council, state federation presidents, and largest locals re public employee pension systems, changes mandated by Social Security amendments, 1978; report in Education Daily re bill to give federal aid to public employee unions for training in collective bargaining, 1975
- Publications, 1996-1997 (Box 40, Folder 12)
  AFT Teacher Tips brochures; Report to AFT Executive Council Task Force on PSRP Issues; GAO report, "Federal Debt: Answers to Frequently Asked Questions"; American Educational Research Association journal, Educational Researcher, vol. 26, no. 3, April 1997; Phi Delta Kappan journal, April 1997; "Dozens of Documents: A catalog of publications and other issues for members, leaders, and the community," fall 1997
- Quality Indicators, 1971-1978 (Box 40, Folder 13)
  Restricted preliminary version, "Quality Inventory: A Schedule of School Variables Related to Quality," (no date)., NYSTA press release re study indicating NYS leads nation in education quality, March 30, 1971; newsletters
- Quality of Work Life, 1982 (Box 40, Folder 14)
  Paper, "A Subjective View of the Quality of Worklife Process: Review of Information Gathered at a Recent George Meany Center Program," by Robert G. Klein, March 1982
- ROTC, 1996 (Box 40, Folder 15)
  Application for teaching certificate for Junior Reserve Officers Training; newspaper clipping; list of high schools offering ROTC in the state; letter from State Education Department noting that ROTC cannot be substituted for required physical education
- Racial Justice and Education: The Black Experience See also: Black Children See also: Human Relations, 1983 (Box 40, Folder 16)
  Description of symposium, sponsored by State Education Department and others.
- Regan/Ambach/Hobart – SED Audit See also: Attendence See also: Dropouts, 1985-1986 (Box 40, Folder 17)
  Report by Office of the State Comptroller of audit of State Education Department, "Monitoring of Programs for Quality of Elementary and Secondary Education," August 9, 1985; letter to state comptroller Edward Regan from NYSUT president Hobart, responding to audit, acknowledging high dropout rate, unmet need for remedial services, asserting that students in New York State are attaining the highest learning achievement than at any other time in the nation's history and in any other nation in the world, May 13, 1986; draft statement at press conference by Regan calling State Education Department an unaccountable, arrogant bureaucracy, decrying lack of available information about educational performance in New York State schools; letter to Regan from Education Commissioner Gordon Ambach responding to statement at press conference, asserting that Education Department has the most comprehensive assessment program in the nation, April 3, 1986
- Board of Regents, Volume XV, 1983 (Box 40, Folder 18)
  November 1983. Meeting agendas; calendar of meetings and special events; biographies of CUNY trustees; committee reports; deputy commissioner's report to the Regents Committee on Higher and Professional Education; report by Regents to Governor and Legislature on State Student Financial Programs; proposed recommendations for state aid to schools; press releases describing Regents actions; handwritten notes by John Schneider
- Board of Regents, Volume XIV, 1983 (Box 40, Folder 19)
  November 1983. List of actions taken by the Board of Regents; material re proposal to establish undergraduate degree program in engineering at SUNY New Paltz; agenda for discussion by Regents Committee on Elementary, Secondary and Continuing Education, including presentation by NYC Board of Education on key educational issues in NYC; handwritten notes by John Schneider
- Board of Regents, Volume VII, 1983 (Box 40, Folder 20)
  October 1983. List of actions taken by the Board of Regents; press releases; deputy commissioner's report and agenda for discussion by Regents Committee on Elementary, Secondary and Continuing Education; handwritten notes by John Schneider
- Board of Regents, Volume XVIII, 1983 (Box 40, Folder 21)
  October 1983. Items for discussion for Regents Committee on Elementary, Secondary and Continuing Education, including Special Report from the NYS Advisory Council on Vocational Education; and for Regents Committee on Higher and Professional Education
- Board of Regents, Volume XVI, 1983 (Box 40, Folder 22)
  September 1983. Deputy commissioner's report for Regents Committee on Higher and Professional Education; agenda for Regents Task Force on Education and Economic Development
- Board of Regents, Volume XV, 1983 (Box 40, Folder 23)
  September 1983. List of actions taken by the Board of Regents; agenda and items for discussion for Regents Committee on Elementary, Secondary and Continuing Education; items for discussion for Regents Committee on Administration, Law and Legislation; report to Gov. Cuomo by the NYS Historical Records Advisory Board
- Board of Regents, Volume XIV, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 1)
  July 1983. Proposed revision to Commissioner's Regulations on professional (i.e., not teaching) licensing, including amending definition of unprofessional conduct
- Board of Regents, Volume XIII, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 2)
  July 1983. List of actions taken by the Board of Regents; major recommendations of the Regents for legislative action; press releases; Regents Policy Statement on Education and Economic Development
- Board of Regents, Volume XII, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 3)
  July 1983. Press releases; handwritten notes by John Schneider; proposed action plan to improve elementary and secondary education results in NYS; items for discussion for Regents Committee on Elementary, Secondary and Continuing Education
- Board of Regents, Volume XI, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 4)
  June 1983. Actions taken; materials for committees and subcommittees, including proposal to increase math and science high school graduation requirement, with description of science curriculum in U.S.S.R. (Russia), China, Japan, and West Germany; handwritten notes by John Schneider
- Board of Regents, Volume IX, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 5)
  May 1983. Actions taken; policy statement, "The Role of Education in Support of NYS's Economic Development"; proposed amendment to Commissioner's Regulations re testing and remedial instruction; status report re serving youth in alternative residences
- Board of Regents, Volume VIII, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 6)
  April 1983. Progress report to Board of Regents on "Education for a Global Perspective: A Plan for New York State"; proposed supplemental budget request for fiscal year 1983-84
- Board of Regents, 1983-1984 (Box 41, Folder 7)
  December, 1983 - February, 1984. Final draft of brochure "Federal Legislation and Education in New York State," with earlier revisions reflected in separate documents
- Board of Regents, 1984 (Box 41, Folder 8)
  December, 1984. Actions taken; materials for committees and subcommittees, including Cultural Education, Vocational Rehabilitation, Economic Development, memo re governor's proposal for state aid to the schools; handwritten notes by John Schneider
- Board of Regents, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 9)
  December, 1983. Final draft of brochure "Federal Legislation and Education in New York State," with earlier revisions reflected in separate documents
- Board of Regents, Volume III, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 10)
  April, 1983. Items for discussion, including deputy commissioner's report (national study of nursing and nursing education, meeting of Medical Manpower Subcommittee, summary of SUNY Trustees meeting), paper re extension of baccalaureate degree powers to two-year colleges; regulation of mental health services, minority enrollments in NYS Veterinary College at Cornell University; materials for action items; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume II, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 11)
  April, 1983. Actions taken; report on school district reorganization; press releases, handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 12)
  March, 1983. Materials for committee and subcommittee meetings, including Cultural Education, Vocational Rehabilitation, Professional Discipline; status report of Chapter 2 of the Education Consolidation and Improvement Act of 1981; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume V, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 13)
  March, 1983. Materials for meeting of Regents Committee on Elementary, Secondary and Continuing Education, including deputy commissioner's report, summary of testimony concerning the proposed state plan for the education of children with handicapping conditions, FY 1984-96; proposed amendment to Commissioner's Regulations; Status Report: Serving Youth in Alternative Residences: A Report to the Board of Regents
- Board of Regents, Volume XVIII, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 14)
  December, 1983. Items for discussion by Committee on Higher and Professional Education, including deputy commissioner's report and Analysis of Current and Future Physician Supply and Requirements in NYS; proposed amendment to Commissioner's Regulations re medical licensing requirements; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume XVII, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 15)
  December, 1983. Report on implementation of regulations re education of children with handicapping conditions ("Study of Part 200 Regulations: Report of Findings")
- Board of Regents, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 16)
  December, 1983. Actions taken; press releases; materials for committee and subcommittee meetings; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume IV, 1983 (Box 41, Folder 17)
  March, 1983. Actions taken; materials for committee and subcommittee meetings, including discussion of authority of Regents to ban corporal punishment; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume V, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 1)
  May, 1981. Actions taken; press releases; materials re disciplinary procedures for teachers; Report to the Regents on the Effectiveness and Efficiency of the Occupational Education System; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume IV, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 2)
  April, 1981. Actions taken; press releases; New York State Plan for Child Nutrition Operations, fiscal year 1982; for the Nutrition Education and Training Program, federal fiscal year 1981; notice of Regents hearing on revision to regulations re handicapped children; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume III, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 3)
  March, 1981. Actions taken; press releases; materials re foreign medical school proposals; materials re nutrition programs; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume II, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 4)
  February, 1981. Actions taken; press releases; final draft, "Federal Legislation and Education in New York State, 1981; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume I, 1981 (Box 42, Folder 5)
  January, 1981. Actions taken; press releases; Statement on Report on Boys and Girls High School, by Regent Yavner; discussion item, Student Performance on Selected Mathematics and Science Examinations; summary of testimony and letters concerning the proposed revisions of Part 200 of the Commissioner's Regulations (handicapped/special ed); handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 6)
  September, 1980. Report, "The Regent's Tentative Statewide Plan for the Development of Postsecondary Education," and comments
- Board of Regents, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 7)
  November, 1980. Actions taken; proposed amendment to regulations for licensing exams for architects; recommendations to legislature for state aid; report on implementation of regulations re teaching as a profession; press releases; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume X, 1980 (Box 42, Folder 8)
  December, 1980. Actions taken; press releases; first draft of brochure, "Federal Legislation and Education in New York State, 1981"; paper, "Education for a Global Perspective: A Presentation to the Board of Regents"; report of the Committee on the Professions on Licensing Petitions
- Board of Regents, 1982 (Box 42, Folder 9)
  February, 1982. Governor's Message on Elementary and Secondary Education and recommendations for state aid to public schools, with comparisons to Regents recommendations; report on implementation of regulations re education of children with handicapping conditions; handwritten notes
- Board of Regents, Volume IV, 1982 (Box 42, Folder 10)
  February, 1982. Actions taken; press releases; NYSUT confidential "Regents' Report Card," listing actions and "inactions"; discussion items, including occupational health and safety legislation affecting school employees, proposed amendment to regulations re guidance program, NYS Migrant Education State Plan; report of Special Task Force on Equity and Excellence in Education; State Education Department Impact Statements on Selected Federal Programs; materials for public hearing on draft state plan for Chapter 2 of the Educational Consolidation and Improvement Act of 1981 (ECIA)
- Board of Regents (folder 1), 1982 (Box 42, Folder 11)